"How Useful Is Personalized Nutrition?"
Personalized nutrition is rooted in the
concept that one size does not fit all,
and who doesn't want
to think they're special?
The concept of personalized nutrition
is inherently appealing to the human ego.
Simple messages recognizing
individuality therefore resonate
deeply with consumers,
explaining the popularity of such
messages in sales and marketing,
even to the point of
manufacturing personalized food
for people's uniqueness,
suggesting 3D Food Printing
as a good candidate
for food customization.
Now, there certainly are some
legitimate differences between people.
Some have a peanut allergy and
keel over if they eat a peanut.
And others have celiac disease
and have to avoid gluten,
or genetically are lactose intolerant.
There's an enzyme mutation
common in some parts of Asia
that protects against alcoholism
because people with it can't
metabolize alcohol as efficiently,
so toxic metabolites build up.
I did a fascinating video about fast
versus slow caffeine metabolizers
and the difference in health benefits.
That actually extends
to athletic performance.
Caffeine is ergogenic,
performance enhancing,
but only in fast metabolizers,
shaving more than a minute
off 10 kilometers of cycling,
whereas slower
metabolizers got no benefit,
or caffeine actually
slows them down,
adding two minutes to their cycling
time, depending on which kind of genes
they have that codes the
enzyme that breaks it down.
But for most people, in most situations,
we are more similar than different.
While there's undoubtedly a specific
minority of individuals who clearly
require a more personalized
approach to nutrition, there is presently
insufficient rationale for truly personalized
nutrition for the majority of people.
Yet there is an astonishing number
of direct-to-consumer genetic testing
companies that have proliferated,
offering personalized nutrition advice,
for example, supplement-hawking
companies claiming to help consumers
optimize micronutrient status on the
basis of a handful of genetic variants.
But the majority of these variants
explain just a few percent
of the difference in levels
between individuals.
Personalized nutrition is part
of a broader push towards
"personalized medicine," also
known as "precision medicine"
given the "massive cultural allure"
of personal control over prevention,
diagnosis, and treatment of disease,
stimulating demand and prompting
intense commercialization.
But unlike monogenetic diseases,
which are rare genetic diseases
caused by a single malfunctioning gene
like hemophilia or sickle cell anemia,
most diseases are caused by a complex
interaction between multiple genes
with environmental factors, which pose
a major challenge for the realization
of personalized medicine.
Take something like
adult stature, for example.
We've found at least 40 locations
on our chromosomes that have been
associated with human height,
which is strongly inherited.
The genes from your parents account
for about 80% of the difference
in height between people, yet all
those dozens of genes we've found
explain only about 5% of
height variation between people.
Researchers find those genetic links
by using what are called genome-wide
association studies, where you
scan through all the chromosomes
and look for statistical
associations between diseases
and any particular stretches of DNA.
Okay, that's interesting,
but what companies marketing
genetic susceptibility tests are doing
is reinterpreting these data as if
they were predictive of individual risks.
But all you're really getting are
modest genetic associations
with a slight increase in the risk of
disease and with little predictive value
when compared to more
significant contributions of things
we already know
like lifestyle behaviors.
Currently, the practice of utilizing
the DNA of an individual to predict
disease has been judged to provide
little or no useful information.
For example, let's say your genetic
analysis says you're at slightly greater
risk for some grave condition compared
to others in your ancestral group.
This person was given advice
to exercise, keep their weight down,
not drink too much alcohol, and eat
fruits, vegetables, and whole grains.
Okay, solid advice,
but this is how we should live
regardless of our genetic risk.
And we all know, or should know,
these simple, bedrock strategies
to reduce the risk of common
chronic diseases in general.
The problem, of course, is that
very few individuals live that way.
Actually, to be more precise,
almost nobody lives that way.
That's not just hyperbole.
Nationwide surveys show that
nearly the entire U.S. population
consumes a diet that is not on par
with even the wimpy dietary
guidelines recommendations.
In other words, almost no one in the
United States is eating a healthy diet.
Studies like that remind us that from
the perspective of public health,
worrying about personalizing
our preventive strategies
based on genetic risk information
borders on the absurd.